# Ning Ma

Department of Computer Science, University of British Columbia, Canada ning.ma@ubc.ca | Google Scholar | Website

## Research Interests

My research interests are in Human-Computer Interaction, Computer-Supported Collaborative Work. *I study the power relationships and the social-economic contexts of workers with respect to other stakeholders* such as customers, platforms, and merchants *in gig platforms*. Particularly, my work attends to workers from marginalized populations including women, financially distressed populations, and rural communities.

## Education

## Pennsylvania State University, University Park, PA

December 2020

Ph.D. in Information Sciences and Technology

Advisor: Benjamin V. Hanrahan

# Concordia University Wisconsin, Mequon, WI

May 2013

B.A. in Mathematics

## **Publications**

#### Journals:

[J1] Johnna Blair, Yuhan Luo, **Ning F Ma,** Sooyeon Lee, and Eun Kyoung Choe. 2018. OneNote Meal: A Photo-Based Diary Study for Reflective Meal Tracking. *Proceedings of American Medical Informatics Association (AMIA '18)*. [Presentation]

#### **Conference Proceedings:**

[C8] **Ning F Ma\***, Veronica Rivera\*, Zheng Yao, Dongwook Yoon. "Brushing it Off": How Women Workers Manage and Cope with Bias and Harassment in Gender Agnostic Gig Platforms." *Proceedings of the 40th annual ACM conference on Human factors in computing systems (CHI 2022).* [Submitted] \*as co-leading author

- [C7] Hanrahan, Benjamin V., Anita Chen, Jiahua Ma, **Ning F. Ma**, Anna Squicciarini, and Saiph Savage. "The Expertise Involved in Deciding which HITs are Worth Doing on Amazon Mechanical Turk." *Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction 5, no. CSCW1 (2021): 1-23.*
- [C6] **Ning F Ma** and Benjamin V Hanrahan. 2020. Unpacking Sharing in the Peer-to-Peer Economy: The Impact of Shared Needs and Backgrounds on Ride-Sharing. *Proceedings of the 23rd annual ACM conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW 2020). Minneapolis, MN, USA.* [PDF]
- [C5] Benjamin V Hanrahan, **Ning F Ma**, Eber Betanzos, Saiph Savage. 2020. Reciprocal Research: Providing Value in Design Research from the Outset in the Rural United States. *In Proceedings of the Eleventh International Conference on Information and Communication Technologies and Development (pp. 1-5).*
- [C4] **Ning F Ma** and Benjamin V Hanrahan. 2019. Part-Time Ride-Sharing: Recognizing the Context in which Drivers Ride-Share and its Impact on Platform Use. *Proc. ACM Hum.-Comput. Interact. 3, GROUP, Article 247 (December 2019), 17 pages. https://doi.org/10.1145/3361128* [PDF][Presentation]

Ning Ma

Page 1 of 4

Updated on: September 2021

- [C3] Anita Chen, Chien Wen Yuan, **Ning F Ma**, and Benjamin V Hanrahan. 2019. Navigating Ride-Sharing Regulations: How Regulations Changed the 'Gig' of Ride-Sharing for Drivers in Taiwan. *Proceedings of the 37th annual ACM conference on Human factors in computing systems (CHI 2019). Glasgow, UK.*
- [C2] **Ning F Ma**, Chien Wen Yuan, Moojan Ghafurian, and Benjamin V Hanrahan. 2018. Using Stakeholder Theory to Examine Drivers' Stake in Uber. *Proceedings of the 36th annual ACM conference on Human factors in computing systems (CHI 2018). Montreal, Canada.* [PDF] [Video][Presentation] (Acceptance rate: 25.7%)
- [C1] Benjamin V Hanrahan, **Ning F Ma**, and Chien Wen Yuan. 2017. The Roots of Bias on Uber. In *Proceedings of the 15th European Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work-Exploratory Papers. European Society for Socially Embedded Technologies (EUSSET)*.

#### Workshops:

[W3] **Ning F. Ma\***, Patrick Lee. Bridging the Negotiation: Reducing Unpaid Work with Freelancers and Clients. 2021. *ACM Computer Supported Cooperative Work 2021 Extended Abstract (CSCW 2021)*. \*as supervisor

[W2] Joice Tang, **Ning F Ma\***, and Dongwook Yoon. Understanding How Customers Attribute Accountability in Food Delivery Breakdowns. 2021. *Joint Proceedings of the ACM IUI 2021 Workshops, April 13–17, 2021, College Station, USA* [PDF] \*as supervisor

[W1] **Ning F Ma** and Benjamin V Hanrahan. 2019. Supporting Relationship for On-Demand Exchanges in Local Communities. *ACM Computer Supported Cooperative Work 2019 Extended Abstract (CSCW 2019)*. *Austin, USA*.

# **Teaching**

Instructor	IST331 Foundation of Human-Centered Design (2020 Spring)
------------	--

Teaching Assistant IST 431 Information Environment (2016 Fall)

IST 413 Usability Engineering (2018 Spring, 2018 Fall, 2019 Spring)

SRA 268 Data Visualization (2019 Fall)

# Experiences

#### **University of British Columbia**

January 2021 - present

Postdoctoral Fellow

Understanding women gig workers and invisible work in online freelancing

#### **Pennsylvania State University**

August 2016 - December 2020

**Graduate Assistant** 

Understanding Ride-Sharing in On-Demand Platforms: Stakes,

Dependency, and Sharing

**Uber Inc.** May 2019 - August 2019

*UX research Intern* 

Conducting user studies to inform why do couriers churn from

Ning Ma Page 2 of 4 Updated on: September 2021

#### platforms

## Wells Fargo Home Mortgage

September 2013 - December 2015

Loan Adjustor

Supported homeowners to short-sale defaulted properties to avoid bankruptcy across the U.S.

# Research Mentoring

#### Joice Tang, undergraduate research assistant at UBC

August 2020 - May 2021

Understanding how customers attribute accountability in food delivery breakdowns.

Co-mentoring with Dongwook Yoon.

#### Tabreek Somani, undergraduate research assistant at UBC

February 2021 - September 2021

Making sense of invisible labor with, and for online freelancers.

Co-mentoring with Dongwook Yoon.

#### Patrick Lee undergraduate research assistant at UBC

February 2021 - present

Doppelganger-phobia and identity fragmentation: understanding perceptions and ethical considerations towards interactive digital clones. Co-mentoring with Dongwook Yoon.

# Scholarship and Professional Activities

#### Student Enrichment Fund - Department of IST at Penn State

2018 - 2020

Travel grant of \$1500/year for 3 years

#### Computing Research Association Grad Cohort San Francisco, CA

April 2018

Women in Computing (funded participation \$1500)

#### Cornell University Summer School, Ithaca, NY

June 2018

Designing Technology for Social Impact (funded participation \$1000)

#### MIT Media Lab, Cambridge, MA

November 2018

All Hands on Deck - Open Ocean Fellow (funded participation \$1000)

# CHIMe mentoring workshop at ACM CHI

2018, 2020, 2021

#### The Future of Work (Places) at ACM CHI. Austin, TX

2021

November 2019

#### Services

1. .

Panelist	2021 Cornell University <u>Summer School</u> on Designing Technology for Social Impact
Reviewer	ACM CSCW 17', 18', 20', 21'
	ACM CHI 19', 20'

Ning Ma Page 3 of 4 Updated on: September 2021

Area Chair ACM CHI 21' late-breaking work

Social Event Chair ACM CSCW 21'

# Selected Press

"How Uber drivers feel about being managed by machines" in Forbes

May 2018

# References

# Benjamin V. Hanrahan

Assistant Professor College of Information Sciences and Technology Pennsylvania State University E383 Westgate Building University Park, PA 16802 bvh10@ist.psu.edu

#### John M. Carroll

Distinguished Professor College of Information Sciences and Technology Pennsylvania State University E319 Westgate Building University Park, PA 16802 jmc56@psu.edu

# **Dongwook Yoon**

Assistant Professor Department of Computer Science University of British Columbia 2366 Main Mall Vancouver, BC Canada V6T 1Z4 yoon@cs.ubc.ca

## Chien Wen (Tina) Yuan

Assistant Professor Graduate Institute of Library & Information Studies National Taiwan Normal University No.162, Sec. 1, Hoping East Rd., Da-an District, Taipei 10610, Taiwan tinachienwenyuan@gmail.com

Updated on: September 2021